<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="City of American Canyon, Cal., Ord. No. 2025-28S">
  <num>2025-28S</num>
  <heading>SUMMARY OF AN ORDINANCE AMENDING AMERICAN CANYON MUNICIPAL CODE TITLE 16 TO REPEAL AND REPLACE THE 2022 CALIFORNIA BUILDING STANDARDS CODE WITH THE 2025 EDITION WITH LOCAL AMENDMENTS; AND REPEAL AND REPLACE THE 2021 INTERNATIONAL PROPERTY MAINTENANCE CODE WITH THE 2024 EDITION AND RELATED MODEL CODES WITH APPENDICES AND AMENDMENTS AS IDENTIFIED THROUGH EXPRESS FINDINGS OF LOCAL NECESSITY</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2026-01-01</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="ord" url="./adopted/2025-28S.pdf" proof="needed">Ord. No. 2025-28S</citation>
      <citation type="bb">City of American Canyon, Cal., Ord. No. 2025-28S</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <introduced>2025-11-18</introduced>
      <adopted>2025-12-02</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <text>Pursuant to Government Code Section 36933 (c), the following constitutes a summary of an Ordinance introduced by the City of American Canyon City Council on November 18, 2025, and scheduled for consideration of adoption on December 2, 2025, at a meeting to be held in the City Council Chambers, 4381 Broadway, Suite 201, American Canyon, California.</text>
  <text class="center">
    <u>ORDINANCE SUMMARY (2025-28S)</u>
  </text>
  <text>The "2025 Building Code Ordinance" updates the City's Municipal Code and incorporate local amendments for portions of the 2025 California Building Standards, thereby creating local editions.</text>
  <text>The 2025 Building Code Ordinance includes Building Code “Local Amendments” that reflect local climatic, geologic, or topographic conditions and Administrative Function amendments which provide the Building Official authority to administer the Building Code with activities, such as: plan review, permit fees, inspections, and penalties. All proposed local amendments to the Building, Residential, Electrical, Mechanical, Plumbing Codes are carried forward from previous Local Amendments adopted by the City Council.</text>
  <text>The Ordinance also includes the 2024 International Property Maintenance Code, and the 2024 International Swimming Pool and Spa Code.</text>
  <text>Adoption of the Building Code Ordinance is not a project that has the potential for causing a significant effect on the environment and therefore is not subject to review under the California Environmental Quality Act (CEQA). In addition, the proposed Ordinance is exempt under the definition of Project in Section 15378 (b) (3) in that it concerns general policy and procedure making.</text>
  <text>A certified copy of the full text of the Ordinance is posted and available for review in the City Clerk's Office at 4381 Broadway, Suite 201, American Canyon, California. This Ordinance shall be in full force and effective on January 1, 2026, and shall be published and posted as required by law.</text>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>Taresa Geilfuss, CMC<br/>City Clerk</text>
    <text>Publication Date: December 9, 2025</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
