<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="City of American Canyon, Cal., 2022-06">
  <num>2022-06</num>
  <heading>AN ORDINANCE OF THE CITY COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF AMERICAN CANYON REPEAL AND REPLACE CHAPTER 13.14.01 THROUGH 13.14.140 OF THE AMERICAN CANYON MUNICIPAL CODE</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2023-01-05</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="ord" url="./adopted/2022-06.pdf" proof="needed">Ord. No. 2022-06</citation>
      <citation type="bb">City of American Canyon, Cal., Ord. No. 2022-06</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <introduced>2022-11-15</introduced>
      <adopted>2022-12-06</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Water Code section 10632 et seq. and California Urban Water Management Planning Act, Water Code section 10610 et seq. mandates that every urban water supplier, prepare and adopt a Water Shortage Contingency Plan meeting the requirements of the code; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the City of American Canyon is an urban water supplier for the purposes of the code, and approved and adopted its most recent City Water Conservation Plan in May 2015; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the City, in accordance with applicable law including requirements of the Code has prepared its Water Conservation Plan and has undertaken certain agency coordination, public notice, public involvement and outreach, public comment, and other procedures in relation to its Water Conservation Plan; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the City has prepared its Water Conservation Plan with its own staff, with the assistance of consulting professionals, and in cooperation with other governmental agencies and has utilized and relied upon industry standards and the expertise of industry professionals in preparing its Water Conservation Plan and has utilized and relied upon the Department of Water Resources 2020 Urban Water Management Plans Guidebook for Urban Water Suppliers (March 2021); and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>in accordance with applicable law, including Water Code sections 10632, and Government Code section 6066, the City made its Water Conservation Plan available for public inspection, and caused to be published within the jurisdiction of the City at least two notices of public hearing regarding the City's Water Conservation Plan, which publication dates included March 23, 2022 and April 6, 2022; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to the public hearing on the Water Conservation Plan the City encouraged the active involvement of diverse social, cultural, and economic elements of the population within the City's service area with regard to the preparation and adoption of the Water Conservation Plan, encouraged input by members of the public and any other interested party regarding all aspects of the Water Conservation Plan, encouraged community input regarding the City's plan for complying with the Water Conservation Act of 2009, considered the economic impacts of complying with the Water Conservation Act of 2009; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the City Council has reviewed and considered the purposes and requirements of the Urban Water Management Planning Act, Water Code section 10632 et seq, and the Water Conservation Act of 2009, the contents of the Water Conservation Plan, the documentation contained in the administrative record in support of the Water Conservation Plan, and all public and agency input received with regard to the Water Conservation Plan, and has determined that the factual analyses and conclusions set forth in the Water Conservation Plan are supported by substantial evidence.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW, THEREFORE</conjunction>
      <text>THE CITY COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF AMERICAN CANYON DOES HEREBY ORDAIN AS FOLLOWS:</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <section>
    <num>1</num>
    <text>: Repeal and Replace Chapters 13.14.01 through 13.14.140 of the City of American Canyon Municipal Code.</text>
    <text>
      <ul proof="needed">
        <li>Chapter 13.14.010 Title</li>
        <li>Chapter 13.14.020 Purpose and intent</li>
        <li>Chapter 13.14.030 Definitions</li>
        <li>Chapter 13.14.060 Water waste prohibitions</li>
        <li>Chapter 13.14.070 Water Conservation stages</li>
        <li>Chapter 13.14.080 Mandatory conservation phase implementation</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>AMENDING CHAPTERS 13.14.01 THROUGH 13.14.140 OF THE CITY OF AMERICAN CANYON MUNICIPAL CODE; and all other ordinances of parts of ordinances in conflict herewith are repealed as set forth in Exhibit A, attached herein and incorporated by reference.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>2</num>
    <text>:  Amend the following Chapters: 13.14.010 Title; 13.14.020 Purpose and intent; 13.14.030 Definitions; 13.14.060 Water waste prohibitions; 13.14.070 Water Conservation stages; 13.14.080 Mandatory conservation phase implementation.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>3</num>
    <text>: No Change to the following Chapters:  13.14.040 AUTHORIZATION; 13.14.050 APPLICATION; 13.14.065 RECYCLED WATER SERVICE REQUIRED; 13.14.090 DURATION OF CONSERVATION STAGES; 13.14.100 DROUGHT SURCHARGE; 13.14.110 Exceptions and application procedures for exceptions; 13.14.120 Violation—Enforcement; 13.14.130 Violation—Penalties; 13.14.140 Violation—Additional remedy.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>4</num>
    <text>: This ordinance shall take effect thirty (30) days after its passage. The effective date of this Ordinance shall be January 5, 2023.</text>
  </section>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>The foregoing Ordinance was introduced at a regular meeting of the City Council of the City of American Canyon, State of California, held on the 15<sup>th</sup> day of November, 2022, by the following vote:</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>AYES:</th>
          <td>Councilmembers Joseph, Oro, Washington, Vice Mayor Aboudamous and Mayor Garcia</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>NOES:</th>
          <td>None</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>ABSTAIN:</th>
          <td>None</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>ABSENT:</th>
          <td>None</td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Ordinance was adopted at a regular meeting of the City Council of the City of American Canyon, State of California, held on the 6<sup>th</sup> day of December, 2022, by the following vote:</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>AYES:</th>
          <td>Councilmembers Joseph, Oro, Washington, and Mayor Garcia</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>NOES:</th>
          <td>None</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>ABSTAIN:</th>
          <td>None</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>ABSENT:</th>
          <td>Vice Mayor Aboudamous</td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>_____________________________</text>
    <text>Leon Garcia, Mayor</text>
    <text>
      <table class="layout-table">
        <tr>
          <td>ATTEST:</td>
          <td class="text-indent-1">APPROVED AS TO FORM:</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>__________________________</td>
          <td class="text-indent-1">__________________________</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Taresa Geilfuss, CMC, City Clerk</td>
          <td class="text-indent-1">William D. Ross, City Attorney</td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
